Guide to the Central Washington University Faculty Papers, Lawrence L. Lowther 1964-2001
Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections
Central Washington University Faculty Papers, Lawrence L. Lowther
1964-2001
Central Washington University, Archives and Special Collections 400 E University Way Ellensburg, WA 98926 (509) 963-1717 http://www.lib.cwu.edu/Archives-Special-Collections archive@cwu.edu
FP-0018
Lowther, Lawrence L.
2.0 cubic feet 5 letter-sized document cases Good condition
This collection consists of correspondence, program and project reports, organizational and departmental minutes, photographs and ephemera collected by Professor Lawrence L. Lowther of Central Washington University from 1964 to 2000.
Biographical Note
Lawrence L. Lowther received his Bachelor of Arts degree in History and Language Arts from the University of Washington in 1952. He completed a Master’s degree in History at the University of Washington in 1959, followed by a Ph.D. in History at the same university in 1964. After graduating in 1952, he worked as a language arts teacher at Twisp High School in Twisp, Washington, from 1952-1954. He then taught language arts at Davenport High School in Davenport, Washington, from 1954-1955, before becoming a social studies teacher at West Valley High School in Yakima, Washington, from 1955-1961. He became Associate Professor of History at General Beadle State College in Madison, South Dakota, from 1964-1965. In 1965 he became a professor of history at Central Washington State College, teaching early American history until his full retirement in 2000. He served as chairman of the History Department from 1979 to 1984. Professor Lowther also played an important role in the growth and development of the History Day program in Washington, serving as the state coordinator (1985-1996) and a member of the National History Day Executive Committee (1990-1996). He was also president, secretary, and executive secretary of the Washington State Council for the Social Studies for many years.
The bulk of the Lawrence Lowther collection contains correspondence related to his teaching career at Central Washington University (1966-2000) and his work with Washington State History Day (1982-1999) and the American Federation of Teachers. Included in the collection are records of the Teacher Education Council (1977-1992) and Washington State Council for Social Studies (1977-1996).
Central Washington University began as the Washington State Normal School in 1891. In 1937, the school was rechristened the Central Washington College of Education. In 1961, the school became Central Washington State College and, finally, in 1977, Central Washington University.
Organized alphabetically by subject title.
Open to the public.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Lowther, Lawrence L.
Central Washington University; Teacher Education Council of State Colleges and Universities (U.S.); Washington State Council for Social Studies
Ellensburg (Wash.)
American Federation of Teachers; Washington (State)--History, Local
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State)
Correspondence
Educators--United States
- Videocassettes (2)--Lawrence Lowther interview (Box-folder 1-1)
- Articles – Bicentennial – Drafts (Box-folder 1-2)
- Articles – Values in History, 1992 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Association of Washington Historians (Box-folder 1-4)
- Athletics and Academics - Correspondence (Box-folder 1-5)
- Book Review Draft – “The American People”, 1982 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Book Review Draft – “Dissent and Disorder” (Box-folder 1-7)
- Correspondence, 1964 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Correspondence, 1965 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Correspondence, 1966 (Box-folder 1-10)
- Correspondence, 1967 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 1-12)
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box-folder 1-13)
- Correspondence, 1970 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 1-15)
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder 1-17)
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 1-18)
- Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 1-19)
- Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 1-20)
- Correspondence, 1977 (Box-folder 1-21)
- Correspondence, 1978 (Box-folder 1-22)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box-folder 2-1)
- Correspondence, 1980 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Correspondence, 1981 (Box-folder 2-3)
- Correspondence, 1982 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Correspondence, 1983 (Box-folder 2-5)
- Correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 2-6)
- Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 2-7)
- Correspondence, 1986 (Box-folder 2-8)
- Correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 2-9)
- Correspondence, 1988 (Box-folder 2-10)
- Correspondence, 1989 (Box-folder 2-11)
- Correspondence, 1990 (Box-folder 2-12)
- Correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 2-13)
- Correspondence, 1992 (Box-folder 2-14)
- Correspondence, 1993 (Box-folder 2-15)
- Correspondence, 1994 (Box-folder 2-16)
- Correspondence, 1995 (Box-folder 2-17)
- Correspondence, 1996 (Box-folder 2-18)
- Correspondence, 1997 (Box-folder 2-19)
- Correspondence, 1998 (Box-folder 2-20)
- Correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder 2-21)
- Correspondence, 2000 (Box-folder 2-22)
- Correspondence (Box-folder 2-23)
- Deposition – Rosco Tolman (Box-folder 2-24)
- Education Department (Box-folder 2-25)
- Edstart (Box-folder 2-26)
- Elderhostel (Box-folder 2-27)
- Ephemera (Box-folder 2-28)
- ETS Question Submissions (Box-folder 2-29)
- Mark Gale Application (Box-folder 2-30)
- General Education Committee (Box-folder 2-31)
- General Honors Program (Box-folder 2-32)
- High School Social Science Curriculum Proposal (Box-folder 2-33)
- Historians’ Bicentennial Newsletter (Nos. 1-3) (Box-folder 2-34)
- History Department – G.Z. Refai (Box-folder 3-1)
- History Department – Floyd Rodine (Box-folder 3-2)
- History Department – Secondary Social Studies Training Proposal (Box-folder 3-3)
- History Department – Secondary Social Studies Training Proposal – Correspondence (Box-folder 3-4)
- History Department – World Civilization Course Proposal (Box-folder 3-5)
- Labor Issues (Box-folder 3-6)
- Lectures – “Bill of Rights” (Box-folder 3-7)
- Lectures – “The Birth of the Constitution and Its Journey through 200 Years” (Box-folder 3-8)
- Lectures – “Revolutions Are Not Mushrooms” (Box-folder 3-9)
- NCATE Accreditation, 1988 (Box-folder 3-10)
- NCATE Precondition Report (Box-folder 3-11)
- NCSS Committee on Religion in Schools (Box-folder 3-12)
- Northwest Association of Schools and Colleges – Evaluation Committee Report, 1989 (Box-folder 3-13)
- OSPI Site Visit, 1987 (Box-folder 3-14)
- Presidential Politics in Historical Perspective (Box-folder 3-15)
- Proposal for a Social Action Component in the High School Social Studies Program (Box-folder 3-16)
- Retirement Planning Committee (Box-folder 3-17)
- Social Science Committee (Box-folder 4-1)
- Sociology 498 (Box-folder 4-2)
- Student Evaluation Summaries, 1973-1987 (Box-folder 4-3)
- Student Evaluation Summaries, 1988-2000 (Box-folder 4-4)
- Summer Institute for School Teachers of Washington State History (Box-folder 4-5)
- Task Force on Interdepartmental Relations (Box-folder 4-6)
- Teacher Education Council – Ad Hoc Committee on Standards in Teacher Education (Box-folder 4-7)
- Teacher Education Council – Basic Programs in Teaching Social Studies in the Middle/Junior High School (Box-folder 4-8)
- Teacher Education Council – Center for the Preparation of School Personnel – Mission Statement (Box-folder 4-9)
- Teacher Education Council – Charter (Box-folder 4-10)
- Teacher Education Council – Committee on Middle Level Programs – Final Report, 1989 (Box-folder 4-11)
- Teacher Education Council – Curriculum Folio – Basic Program in Social Studies (Box-folder 4-12)
- Teacher Education Council – Direction and Challenge, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 4-13)
- Teacher Education Council – Elementary Education Academic Component (Box-folder 4-14)
- Teacher Education Council – Membership Roster, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 4-15)
- Teacher Education Council – Memoranda, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 4-16)
- Teacher Education Council – Memoranda, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 4-17)
- Teacher Education Council – Middle Level Teacher Training Project (Box-folder 4-18)
- Teacher Education Council – Minutes (intermittent), 1977-1991 (Box-folder 4-19)
- Teacher Education Council – Policy for Recruitment and Retention of Minority Students in Teacher Education (Box-folder 4-20)
- Teacher Education Council – Statement of Organization and Procedure, 1978 (Box-folder 4-21)
- Teacher Education Council – A Suggested Academic Component for Candidates for Elementary Education Certification (Box-folder 4-22)
- Teacher Education Council – Survey of Social Science Coursework of Elementary Teacher Candidates (Box-folder 4-23)
- Teacher Education Council – Task Force on Graduate Teacher Education – Report on Graduate Education for Teachers, 1988 (Box-folder 4-24)
- Teacher Education Council – Task Force on Selection, Retention, and Counseling of Teacher Education Students – Report, 1985 (Box-folder 4-25)
- Teacher Education Council – Teacher Education Program – Future Goals and Directions, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 4-26)
- Teacher Education Program Proposal, 1990 (Box-folder 4-27)
- Textbook Critiques (Box-folder 4-28)
- Undergraduate Curriculum Committee – Minutes, 1973 (Box-folder 5-1)
- University Curriculum Committee – Minutes, 1990 (Box-folder 5-2)
- U.S. Survey Readings Project (Box-folder 5-3)
- Cynder Viles – Centralia Massacre Monument (Box-folder 5-4)
- Vita / Professional Service Record (Box-folder 5-5)
- Washington State American Revolution Bicentennial Commission – Article with L. Lowther (Box-folder 5-6)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies (Box-folder 5-7)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 5-8)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Correspondence, 1980-1991 (Box-folder 5-9)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Executive Board Elections (Box-folder 5-10)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Executive Committee – Minutes, 1978-1985 (Box-folder 5-11)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Executive Committee – Minutes, 1986-1996 (Box-folder 5-12)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Financial Reports, 1982-1993 (Box-folder 5-13)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Interest Inventory Survey (Box-folder 5-14)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Miscellaneous (Box-folder 5-15)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Newsletter (Intermittent), 1970-1977 (Box-folder 5-16)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Newsletter, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 5-17)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Newsletter, 1990-1996 (Box-folder 5-18)
- Washington State Council for the Social Studies – Workshop – Issues in American History (Box-folder 5-19)